<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Gods goodnes and mercy Layd open in a sermon, preached at Pauls-Crosse on the last of Iune. 1622. By Mr Robert Harris, pastour of the church of God in Hanvvell in Oxfordshire.</title>
            <author>Harris, Robert, 1581-1658.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 58 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02698</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 12831</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116602</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851818</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851818</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17110</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02698)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17110)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1104:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Gods goodnes and mercy Layd open in a sermon, preached at Pauls-Crosse on the last of Iune. 1622. By Mr Robert Harris, pastour of the church of God in Hanvvell in Oxfordshire.</title>
                  <author>Harris, Robert, 1581-1658.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 29, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Davvson for Iohn Bartlet, and are to be sold at the Guilt Cup in the Gold-smiths Row in Cheap-side,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1622.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>On Psalms CXXXVI, 1.</note>
                  <note>With a final postscript leaf.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17110:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17110:1"/>
            <p>GODS GOODNES AND MERCY.</p>
            <p>LAYD OPEN IN A SERMON, PREACHED AT <hi>PAVLS</hi>-CROSSE ON THE LAST OF <hi>I<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NE.</hi> 1622.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>BY</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> ROBERT HARRIS, Paſtour of the Church of GOD at HANVVELL in <hi>Oxfordſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>GAL. 6.10.</bibl>
               <p>As we haue therefore opportunitie, let vs doe good to all men, eſpecially to them that are of the houſhold of Faith.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed by IOHN DAVVSON for IOHN BARTLET, and are to be ſold at the Guilt Cup in the Gold-ſmiths Row in <hi>Cheap-ſide.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1622.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:17110:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17110:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL, <hi>Sir</hi> BAPTIST HICKS, Iuſtice of Peace in <hi>Middleſex, Grace and Peace.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Should much forget my ſelfe, if (whilſt I preſſe others to <hi>Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> &amp; <hi>Mercy</hi>) I ſhould forget yours to my natiue Country; <note place="margin">Campden in Glouc. ſhyre.</note> there you haue done good, (to the houſe of God) not onely in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward buildings and ornaments, <note place="margin">M. Lilly.</note> but in ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling a Preacher, where before was none, and ſuch a one as cannot eaſily be equalled in eminency of gifts: There alſo, you haue
<pb facs="tcp:17110:3"/>exerciſed <hi>(Mercy)</hi> in building ſuch an Almeſ-houſe, as that, I know not what may be added thereto, vnleſſe hereafter, you ſhall ſee cauſe to ſet over the blind and lame, and deafe (who are leſſe able to repaire to, and profit by the publique Miniſtery) a more private Teacher and Catechiſt. Sir, I thanke God, I could never yet the Art of flattery, neither will your Wiſedome (if I know you) brooke the trade. It ſufficeth, that I haue in a line or two recommended to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers practiſe your example; and conveyed to Poſteritie, my thankfulneſſe, with your bountie. If God make me able, I ſhall (haply) doe it hereafter in a better manner, In the meane, I beſeech you to accept my preſent thankes wrapt vp in a dead Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and ſicke Epiſtle, and ſtill continue to loue his Country, who ſtill reſts</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Hanwell</hi> in <hi>Oxon:</hi> ſhire, <date>Iuly 9. 1622.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your <hi>WORSHIPS</hi> in all thankefulnes and dutie <hi>ROBERT HARRIS.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="chart">
            <pb facs="tcp:17110:3"/>
            <p>In this <hi>Pſalme,</hi> we haue
<list>
                  <item>1. A dutie, <hi>Thankfulnes,</hi> deſcribed from its common nature, <hi>Confeſsion.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. Arguments, from the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of our prayſes, <hi>God,</hi> conſidered
<list>
                        <item>1. In himſelfe.
<list>
                              <item>1. In his ſimple being, <hi>Iehovah,</hi> verſ. 1.</item>
                              <item>2. In his ſecond being, <hi>viz.</hi> his properties, reduced to
<list>
                                    <item>1. Graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes
<list>
                                          <item>1. Simply good.</item>
                                          <item>2. Reſpectiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mercifull.</item>
                                       </list>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>2. Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.
<list>
                                          <item>1. Power is his. verſ. 2.</item>
                                          <item>2. Dominion is his. v. 3.</item>
                                       </list>
                                    </item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>2. In his works delivered
<list>
                              <item>1. In generall, they are all wonderfull. verſ. 4.</item>
                              <item>2. In ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall.
<list>
                                    <item>1. Such as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne the whole world.
<list>
                                          <item>Creation in the parts thereof. verſ. 5 6. 7.</item>
                                          <item>Preſervation &amp; government. verſ. 8.9.</item>
                                       </list>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>2. Such as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne the Church.
<list>
                                          <item>1. In her firſt Planta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion verſ. 10-23.</item>
                                          <item>2. In her ſetled e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, her bleſſings
<list>
                                                <item>
                                                   <hi>Privatiue.</hi> v. 23.24.</item>
                                                <item>
                                                   <hi>Poſitiue.</hi>
                                                </item>
                                                <item>Earthly. verſ. 25.</item>
                                                <item>Spirituall. verſ. 26.</item>
                                             </list>
                                          </item>
                                       </list>
                                    </item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:17110:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17110:4"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> To the Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>ENTLE READER;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Vnderſtand, that I was then Summoned to the Croſſe, when I was not in caſe, either to Studie or to ſpeake; the former ſtraight, (when I could not be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed) forced me to a familiar and eaſie Text, the later to a briefe and ſhort kind of ſpeech, which car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried with it an appearance of that, which I ever ſhund, <hi>Affectation</hi> and <hi>Obſcuritie.</hi> It may bee, thine Eye will conceiue mee better then thine Eare, and therefore I yeelde to importunity, and preſent my ſelfe to thy view, entreating <hi>2.</hi> things of thee, <hi>1. Charity, 2. Conſcience,</hi> Charity towards the Printer, in caſe ſome faults (in my abſence) eſcape him: towards me, in caſe ſo frequent quotations offend thee: my now pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe agrees with my ancient Iudgement; at home, my people neither vnderſtand nor deſire tongues, and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Authorities, and therefore I am ſparing, on the other ſide, when I fall vpon an Auditorie that conceiues and receiues both, I vſe both, as I ſee my advantage. All is thine if thou canſt be content, and wilt add <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:17110:5"/>(the ſecond thing) to <hi>charity.</hi> It grieues my ſoule to ſee the guiſe of many hearers; they deſire novel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: when they haue heard, théy iudge the man and his method<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and then ſit downe, ſeldome practiſing what is preached. Reader be not ſuch an hearer, leſt thou coſen thy ſelfe <hi>Iames 1.22.</hi> thou here ſeeſt, that if thou be of God, and Gods goodneſſe, and ſpecial mercy ſhall be thine, thou muſt be good, and do good, be mercifull and ſhew mercie, the times require this, the Lord expects this, our vnthankfulnes and vnfruitfulnes hath welmoſt vndone vs, if wee, who haue more peace in the State, more preaching in the Church, then any other knowne Nation vnder Heauen, be not more fruitful and aboun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dant in goodnes, then other people, our light wilbe turnd into darknes, our Sunne into blood: what ſhall I ſay? or to whom ſhall I turne my ſelfe? we cal til we are hoarſe, we ſpeake till we ſpit forth our lungs, yet will not the Sonnes of Men heare vs, they wil not heare, I ſay (with teares) they will not heare, we can doe no good: O Lord perſwade <hi>Iaphet</hi> for we can not, and be mercifull to this barren Countrey: Reader I leaue thee, adding to the <hi>Martyrs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Fox <hi>his</hi> Martyrol. &amp;c.</note> pray, pray, pray, worke, worke, worke.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in the Lord, RO. HARRIS.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:17110:5"/>
            <head>GODS GOODNES AND MER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CIE, LAID OPEN IN A Sermon at <hi>Pauls Croſſe,</hi> on the laſt of <hi>Iune.</hi> 1622.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Pſalme 136. verſe 1.</bibl>
                  <p>Prayſe ye the Lord, becauſe he is good: for his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie endureth for ever &amp;c.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Pſalme cleeres it ſelfe, and therefore a Title nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded not, it anſwers all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions: and therefore the Arguments are generall, it was ſung by courſe, and therefore the burthen is ſtil the ſame: In it we haue a Dutie preſſed, and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments preſſing: the Dutie is thankefulneſſe, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered from its common nature; <hi>Confeſsion:</hi> (our praiſes are but acknowledgments of Gods excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies.) The Arguments are drawne from the Obiect of our prayſes, <hi>God,</hi> conſidered firſt in himſelfe; Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, in his workes: in himſelfe conſidered, he is apprehended by a firſt and ſecond Act of our vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding;
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:17110:6"/>Firſt, in his moſt ſimple being (confeſſe to <hi>Iehovah.</hi>) Secondly, in his ſecond being, (to ſpeake as wee conceiue things) in his properties. Theſe mentioned are, firſt, <hi>Gratiouſneſſe;</hi> Secondly, <hi>Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe;</hi> for the firſt, he is firſt ſimply <hi>(Good)</hi> and then in a reſpect <hi>(Mercifull,)</hi> for the ſecond, his is Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, he is (Gods of Gods) Gods in the plurall, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe al powers are his, (God of Gods) in an hebrew ſuperlatiue, becauſe he is far aboue all Gods, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſo reputed or deputed; that great, that ſtrong God, as <hi>Moſes</hi> expounds the phraſe. <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.7. next, Kingdome is his: Hee is (Lords of Lords) in the ſame ſence, that is the Monarch and Emperour, of Princes and States; nowe if power be his, and Kingdome his, Glory is his alſo, therefore <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> confeſſe it, ſayth the Pſalmiſt: this is the firſt Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument from Gods bleſſed ſelfe, the ſecond, from his workes, we leaue for haſt, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Of the Action <hi>(Confeſſe,)</hi> the Obiect <hi>(Iehovah)</hi> ſome thing at home. <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> &amp; <hi>Mercie,</hi> offer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues next; and firſt, <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> as the more gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>God is good.</hi> This point is plaine, a principle not needing proofe; there be (ſayth nature in the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher) ſome confeſſed goods, <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Ariſt. Rhet. li 1. c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>&amp; inde:</hi>
               </note> of theſe, God is the cheife, nay all theſe in one, like an abſolute pearle, that containes all beauties in it ſelfe, no <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion</hi> will denie goodneſſe, where he yeelds a God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, wee haue therefore ſayd enough for proofe, when we haue once ſayd what goodnes is, and how it is affirmed of God.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> For the firſt, <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> is the perfection of things,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:17110:6"/>for which they are deſireable, perfection imports freedome from all defects, and fulnes of all excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies, and is cheifely ſeene in the being, working, end of things; that which hath the nobleſt being, and therefore ende, and therefore operations, is ever beſt and moſt deſireable: Deſire is the reaching of the Soule after that that likes vs, becauſe it is like vs: Now the All-ſufficient God is his owne <hi>Being,</hi> his owne <hi>Act, or rule in Action,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bonum onmis boni. <hi>Aug.</hi> de Trinit. li. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> yea he is the Author of all good, and ende, &amp; deſire (in naturall reſpects) and therefore the perfection of all, and all perfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and goodneſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> For the ſecond, God is, firſt, <hi>eſſentially good, good without goodneſſe,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Auſtin</hi>). Creatures be good, but not goodneſſe; their nature is good, but good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is not their nature, but the nature and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of God (ſayth the Chriſtian Phyloſopher) is goodneſſe, nature and goodneſſe differ not in him, but onely in a reſpect.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>cauſally good;</hi>
               <note place="margin">v. <hi>Aqui.</hi> quaſt. de bon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> not as the forme of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular goods, but as the worker of all; the ende, that terminates and perfects all.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, (which followes vpon the former) <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minently good:</hi> firſt, in Order, Nature, Worth; and laſtly, originally, and abſolutely the onely good.</p>
            <p>This Doctrine cals more for practiſe then proofe, becauſe as in nature, ſo here, the ſweeteſt things are moſt abuſed, and being abuſed, proue moſt dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous. God is good, let vs put it to a good vſe; <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>
               </label> firſt, for <hi>Humbling,</hi> ſee what we were once, good: for of goodnes, can come nothing but goodnes; ſecondly What we are now by nature, bad; for firſt, we are
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:17110:7"/>ſunke as farre from God as Hell is from heaven; hee is <hi>holy,</hi> we profane, he <hi>wiſe,</hi> we fooliſh, he <hi>true,</hi> wee falſe, he <hi>good,</hi> we naught. Secondly from this diſpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion growes hatred of Gods holineſſe, in his word, worſhip, people, preſence, every way. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, from this hatred ſprings loue to his Enemies, the World, Fleſh<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Satan. Fourthly from this loue a liſtning to what fleſh ſhal propound, and Satan ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt, and thence a capacitie and poſſibilitie of being monſtrous in life, and blaſphemous to the death.</p>
            <p>Oh what a peece of ground is mans heart nowe become wherein no ſpiritualnes thrives, vnleſſe Power it ſelfe plant it? wherin, <hi>Pride, Murther, Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, Sodomy, Blaſphemie, Atheiſme,</hi> eyther doth or ſoone may ſeede? this curſed nature, this renders vs as odious, as goodnes doth amiable, and this muſt be ſeene, if ever we will be ſaved. Now the glaſſe that detects badnes is Gods goodneſſe, by his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and workes we ſee ours, as by the ſunne wee ſee motes, and filth by light; but God is a light too ſtrong for our ſence; <note place="margin">Strato. <hi>apud</hi> Iuſtin. <hi>lib.</hi> 18.</note> True, therefore we muſt with him (in the ſtory) looke for the Sunne in the Weſt, not in the Eaſt: behold the Lord, as he is reflected and refracted, firſt in the glaſſe of his creatures, and his workes, Secondly, in the face of his deareſt Son, ſo wee ſhall ſee (at one view) vnſpeakeable beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and deformitie; that in God, this in vs: ſo way and overture will be made for that firſt, ſecond, and third of Chriſtianitie, true humilitie: <note place="margin">Aug. <hi>Epiſt.</hi>
               </note> ſo Gods goodneſſe will be admired; mans wickednes ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred all the errours of the times, and incongrui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of action will be ſoone reſolved into their firſt
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:17110:7"/>principle, eſtrangement from, and diſtruſt in this goodnes of God.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, ſee what we ſhould be, good, goodnes is even admirable, <note place="margin">Plut.</note> and therefore (ſayth the Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopher) imitable. Now the 119. <hi>Pſal. verſ.</hi> 68. tels vs, that God is good, and duth good, and he is our Coppy and rule.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt therefore wee muſt bee good, and then doe good. firſt the ſap muſt be good, and then the fruit; for as things be, ſo they worke; the effuſion of the ſap (the firſt act of our converſion) is Gods act, our will prevents it not, but followes it. The ſecond act (of fructifying) is ours, vnder God: for when God hath tuned and doth touch vs, we doe moue, and whileſt the ſpirit imbreathes vs, we turne about like the Mill: in neither wee muſt bee wanting to our ſelues, but concurre, in this as agents, in that as pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents, and as our liberty (in externall acts) is ſtill ſome, ſo muſt our endevours be anſwerable. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Quoad externa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diſciplinam,</hi> as to come to Church, to heare, &amp;c.</note> Firſt we muſt haue the patience to heare (what ſoever wanton wits may talke of the wills virginitie or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther exemptions of the higher faculties) that in our fleſh dwels no ſpirituall goodnes, all our good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe dwels out of our ſelues in Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that it is Gods owne hand, that ſlends vs from the firſt, and ſets vs in the ſecond <hi>Adam.</hi> And thirdly that he doth this by his owne meanes, &amp; therfore we muſt tender our ſelues to his meanes, waiting till hee (who ſpeakes in working, and workes in ſpeaking) ſhall pleaſe to ſpeake life into the Soule, by the eare.</p>
            <p>Thus are we made trees, <note place="margin">Eſay 55.3.</note> being ſuch, wee muſt <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:17110:8"/>in the ſecond place, beare: and heere lies our buſines, our errand hither, is not to pleaſe or preach man, but to call for fruite <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.34. you are trees in Gods vineyard, well planted, fenced, huſbanded, what is your fruite? your Land is good, your Law is good, your Cittie good, your Sermons good, what be you? Is your truite none? Heare our bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Saviour, every Tree, every Man, Houſe, Citty, Nation, <note place="margin">Math. 7.19.</note> that beares not fruite, is for the fire: Is <note place="margin">18.</note>your fruite bad? Heare againe, a good Tree can not bring foorth bad fruite, and the ground that brings forth briers after ſhowers muſt be burnt. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.8. You haue received the raine of Heaven, and muſt be as the raine and dewe, <hi>Mic.</hi> 5.7. els the curſe is neare. Is your goodneſſe onely Morall? heare your Saviour, <hi>Every branch that beares not fruite in me, he takes away. Ioh.</hi> 15.2. Your workes muſt be the workes of God, wrought from God, for God, in God, according to God, elſe they are but ſhining ſins. Is your goodnes ſpirituall? heare againe, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe a man abide in me he is caſt out, caſt into the fire and burnt, <hi>Iohn</hi> 15.6. Behold, if an other ſhould crie <hi>fire, fire, fire,</hi> thus in your ſtreetes, you woulde be all awakened; our bleſſed Saviour cries fire, if your fruite be none, fire, if bad, fire, if not ſpirituall, fire, if not laſting.</p>
            <p>Oh be afraid of this conſuming fire, and as you heare the words, ſo doe the workes of God. Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, (we muſt know) is not a name, goodneſſe a word, it is actiue like fire, communicatiue like light, as the life of things ſtands in goodnes, ſo the life of goodneſſe in action. The cheifeſt goods are
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:17110:8"/>moſt actiue, the beſt good a meere Act, &amp; the more good we doe, the more god-like and excellent wee bee; what is the excellency of meates? goodnes, what of wines? goodnes, what of grounds? good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, what of all? goodnes: what is mans comfort in life? what in death? what after? whatever? goodnes. This is the man, <note place="margin">Eccle. 12.</note> the whole man, no crowne to this in life, no comfort to this in death, no tombe to this after death, no gaine to this in the day of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts. Well done good ſervant, enter into thy maſters ioy. Glory, and honour, and peace, is to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very worker of goodnes, <note place="margin">Rom. 2.</note> whether Iew or Gentile, bond or free, rich or poore, wiſe or ſimple, weake or ſtrong; if a worker of righteouſneſſe, hee is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, aſſiſted, rewarded, therefore worke.</p>
            <p>Now as you muſt be preſſed to, <note place="margin">Tit. 3. 1.</note> and rich in every good worke, ſo cheifely in the beſt, for kinde or vſe, that is, good ſpirituall, and common, for the firſt, as ſpirituall gifts, ſo acts are moſt deſireable. Man never liues till the life of God liue in him, and all that he doth be either a ſpirituall act, or (at leaſt) ſpiritually acted, <note place="margin">Zach. 14.</note> holineſſe muſt be written (<hi>Zacha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi> tels vs) vpon our bridles, when we warre; vpon our cups, when we drinke: In ſhort, the kingdome of God, muſt firſt bee ſought and ſet vpp in vs and ours; and, what we may, advanced among others, in the meanes of it and maintenance for it. And heere the rich may ioyne in one both theſe goods (ſpirituall and common) ſome Churches (you ſee) want men, ſome men Churches and meanes, I bluſh, I bleede to ſpeake it, able men are ready to hire out themſelues for bread, and excellent wits
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:17110:9"/>hang the head, for want of watering, gaſping like fiſhes out of the water, being out of all, both meanes and hopes; if there be any true blood yet running in your veines, you that can feede Birds and Dogs, ſtarue not Grace and Learning. Children might be Schollers, <note place="margin">Obad. laſt verſe.</note> Schollers Preachers, Preachers Saviours, and that of Thouſands did not dogs eate the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens bread.</p>
            <p>Secondly, you muſt ayme at the common good, for that is ſtill the greateſt good; and heere two rules, firſt, if you will be for the publike, you muſt be good in private: beare your owne fruite, <note place="margin">Pſal. 1.</note> worke in your owne hines, man your owne oares, and make good your owne ſtanding. Happy is that body, wherein the eye ſees, the eare heares, the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſanguifies &amp;c. Happy that houſe, wherein the Maſter rules, the man runs, the head leades, and the body follows; Happie that State, wherein the Cobler meddles with his laſt, the Tradeſman with his ſhop, the Student with his booke, the Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler with State, the Prince with the Scepter, and each Creature liues in his owne Element; but woe be to the Heathens armie, when all wil be Captaines, and none Souldiers, woe to that body that will be all head; members miſplaced are neither for vſe nor eaſe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, we muſt ſhoote at the common white, that is, though you bee private in your ſtandings, yet you muſt be publike in your affections, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendements.</p>
            <p>For the firſt; <note place="margin">Richard 1.</note> as King <hi>Richard</hi> beſtowed himſelfe diverſly, at his death, ſo muſt wee in life; <hi>Bohemia</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:17110:9"/>claimes a part in our loue, the <hi>Palatinate</hi> a part, the <hi>Churches</hi> abroad, <hi>our Brethren</hi> at home, a part: at home, in ſelling we muſt be buyers, in lending bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowers, in viſiting patients, in comforting mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; abroad, we muſt in our owne peace conſider their warres, feele them panting, ſee them bleeding, heare them ſcriching; <hi>O husband, O wife, O my child, my child, O mother, mother, mother, my father is ſlaine, my brother is torne, my legge is off, my guts be out, halfe dead, halfe aliue, worſe then either, becauſe neither.</hi> O that wee had heartes to bleede over them, and to pray for the peace of Ieruſalem.</p>
            <p>For the ſecond, our thoughts muſt all meete in the common good, like ſo many lines in a Center, ſtreames in the Sea; Chriſt Ieſus <hi>pleaſed not himſelfe</hi> ſayth <hi>Saint Paul,</hi> hee <hi>dyed for vs,</hi> ſayth <hi>Saint Iohn,</hi> therefore wee muſt for our brethren; one mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber will die for all, one heathen for manie; if we muſt die for the common good, muſt wee not liue to it? If all muſt, muſt not the more publike per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon? Yes you Lawyers (to Inſtance) muſt be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon bleſſings, and not ſeeke your owne, you muſt (with <hi>Papinian</hi>) reiect bad cauſes, and ripen good, there goes but a paire of Sheares beween a protrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Lawyer and cheating Mountebanke, that ſets his Client backward and foreward like a man at Cheſſe, and proues a butcher to the ſillie ſheepe, which ran to him from the Graſier.</p>
            <p>You Land-lords muſt be common too, <note place="margin">v. <hi>Grin</hi> Epiſt. ad Synopſin Hiſt. bominis.</note> if with that Duke you will truſt your Tennants with your throat, you muſt not hurt theirs, you are heads of Townes, the head ſhould care for the leaſt toe, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſure
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:17110:10"/>if it wound not the heart, yet treads it hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie on the toes of a State; force not men by wrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king rents, by over laying Commons, and picking quarrels to vndoe themſelues, betray not Townes as <hi>Rome</hi> did <hi>Carthage</hi> with a diſtinction, wee will ſaue the Cittic, but deſtroy the Towne: a poore man in his houſe is like a Snayle in his ſhell, cruſh that, and you kill him, ſay therefore with thy ſelfe, my Tennant is a man, not a beaſt, were he a beaſt, yet a righteous man is mercifull to his beaſt, a breeding Bird muſt not haue her neſt deſtroyd, a yong kidd muſt not be ſod in his mothers milke, what will become of me and mine, if I deſtroy the neſt of breeding Chriſtians, and having chopt them to the pot, <note place="margin">Mich. 3.3.</note> ſeethe old and yong in one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers blood?</p>
            <p>You <hi>Patrones</hi> muſt bee for the common good alſo, preferre many ſoules to one tenth, when you be to chooſe a Shepheard; let the queſtion be that of theirs in the Goſpell, <hi>who is worthy?</hi> and the deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, <hi>detur digniori;</hi> when you preſent, preſent not a <hi>Prometheus</hi> ſacrifice, skin and bone without fleſh; when you haue preſented, <note place="margin">Zach 5.4.</note> feare <hi>Zacharies</hi> curſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt perjurie and ſacriledge, if perjurie dwell in the Parſonage, and robbery in the Mannor, the curſe of God will pull downe both. Laſtly, when you haue a Prophet, bee you <hi>Patrones,</hi> ſtudie his peace, as he doth yours, what Law it may be, after vowes to enquire I doe not know, ſure I am, <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> ſayth, it is deſtruction, deſtruction of ſome e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, of many ſoules; whilſt the nurſe wants bread the children want milke, ſo both cry and both are
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:17110:10"/>heard, and woe be to him that hath a crie of Soules againſt him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nobles,</hi> I know not whether they frequent this place or not, if ſo, I would entreat them to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, what the Story ſayth of ſome men, that they are Medicinable from top to toe, <note place="margin">Plin. <hi>li.</hi> 28. <hi>c.</hi> 3.</note> and ſuch ſhould they be. Firſt, they ſhould heale themſelues, becauſe their actions are all exemplary; then their families, by eſtabliſhing <hi>Nebuchadnezzars</hi> order, <note place="margin">Dan. 3.29.</note> that no man ſpeake (much leſſe doe) any thing amiſſe againſt the God of Heaven; thirdly, the oppreſſed and wounded; they ſhould reſcue the poore, as did no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Iob;</hi> plead for them, ride for them, ſpeake to Maieſtie it ſelfe for them, where povertie hath not acceſſe. So ſhall they be common bleſſings, <note place="margin">Filij herôum noxae.</note> and prevent the cenſure of former Ages.</p>
            <p>We cloſe this Vſe with <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> and <hi>Iuſtices (Itinerant,</hi> or others); <note place="margin">Rom. 13. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Saint <hi>Paul</hi> tells them their errand; it is the common good, and chalkes out their way; they muſt be terrors and comforts: firſt, terrors to the evill, elſe evill-doers will be a ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror to them, for ſin is impudent and incroaching, as experience hath taught vs: <hi>bribery</hi> will be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times bolder then <hi>innocency, falſhood</hi> then <hi>truth;</hi> a man that doth more then deliberate of Rebellion (which yet a <hi>Tacitus</hi> could call <hi>Rebellion</hi>), <note place="margin">Lib. <hi>2.</hi> Hiſtor.</note> he will embarke himſelfe in actions of State, embroyle Kingdomes, transferre, for his publique good, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> Carer. <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>ae poteſſt.</hi> Ro: Pont. <hi>c.</hi> 19.</note> any Crowne, ſpeake moſt baſely of annointed Princes, and yet ſuch a man as this will be, neere hand, heard as loud from the Barre, as Iuſtice from the Bench; a <hi>Gentleman-ſwearer, drunkard, whore-maſter,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:17110:11"/>ſtabber,</hi> will ſoone out-ſtare a Iuſtice, an Alderman; and a Noble-mans mans man will ſo amaze Iuſtice (if ſhee take not the more heart) that ſhee is left ſpeechleſſe a long time after. O <hi>Iob, Phineas, Nehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah, &amp;c.</hi> whats become of your ſpirit? You would driue ſinne and ſinners into their holes; now they dare the light, and ſtare Iuſtice in the face, as if they would out-face her: ariſe (ye living Images of God) cloth your ſelues with zeale as with a cloake, put on Iuſtice as a garment, vnderſtand, that there is a King in <hi>Iſraell,</hi> a God in heaven; and make ſin vnderſtand, that you haue zeale in your hearts, and a ſword in your hands.</p>
            <p>Secondly, You muſt be incouragers of goodnes; goodneſſe (I ſay) both ſpirituall and morall, reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and righteouſneſſe; for Religion, where is zeale comely, if not there? when, if not now, when falſe zeale blazeth, and true cooles? View a zealous Papiſt (in that name and reſpect, better then a meere Newter) and he dares tell vs to our heads, that our Religion is errour, our ſelues heretickes, our end deſtruction; that one Heaven cannot hold vs hereafter, one Church now, that living and dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Lutherans,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cam. <hi>ca.</hi> 10. Barel. Paraen. Briſt. Mot. 36. Coſter <hi>reſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ad Ruf.</hi> Luc. Oſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>and: &amp;c.</note> we ſhall be certainely damned; if we be not, he will be damned for vs: Now if our Faith ſtand vpon better pillars then his, why ſhould not we be as reſolute and confident as he? View againe the Atheiſt, and he flieth vpon Religion, as a Bird vpon the Candle; he diſgraces it, and will not you then grace it? He ſmites it, and will not you defend it? Yes, Religion calls in your ſword to her ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour, chiefely when ſhe is oppoſed in her <hi>Prophets,</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:17110:11"/>they are the men of ſorrowes; <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Vocabula amiſimus &amp;</hi> Saluſt.</note> they find the <hi>Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian</hi> true, that we haue loſt the names againe the Atheiſt, of things: <hi>Darkeneſſe</hi> is called <hi>light, light darkeneſſe;</hi> the <hi>Shepheard</hi> is hunted, and the <hi>Foxe</hi> hunts him: Many a man cryes out of blaſphemie againſt God and the King, and the blaſphemie is but this; <hi>Naboth</hi> will not part with a peece of his Fleeſe; many a fearefull Bill is framed againſt a Preacher, when the Enditement ſhould run thus; <hi>Bonus vir, ſed ideo malus, quia Chriſtianus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tertull: <hi>Apol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loget.</hi>
               </note> at leſt <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinuncius.</hi> My <hi>Fathers,</hi> and reverent <hi>Iudges,</hi> open your mouthes in the cauſe of the afflicted; remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, that you owe your Hoods, Gownes, Liues, ſelues to the Goſpell; did not our Miniſtry awe mens Conſciences, nor you, nor the world would be one yeare elder; ſhould you ceaſe to countenance vs in our righteous cauſes, you ſhould betray your right hand with the left.</p>
            <p>Now as <hi>Religion</hi> brings the greateſt good, and therefore muſt be moſt reſpected; ſo <hi>Iuſtice</hi> the next, and therefore muſt be carefully adminiſtred. And here we ſhall not need to mind you of the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratours <hi>duſt,</hi> or the Heathens <hi>note,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tac: <hi>l.</hi> 15. <hi>Annal.</hi>
               </note> How that many more offend by ſeeking favour, then offending; it ſhall ſuffice to referre your wiſedomes to two Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in <hi>Iob;</hi> the firſt, <note place="margin">Chap. 15.34.</note> is Chap. 15. verſ. 34 and its this; <hi>Fire ſhall conſume the Tabernacles of Bribery:</hi> if Bribery (however diſguiſed) get into the houſe, whether by the maſter or miſtreſſe, or ſonne, or ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant God will fire it out, or fire the houſe over it. The ſecond, is Chap. 13. verſ. 10. <note place="margin">Chap. 13.10.</note> 
               <hi>He will ſurely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue you, if you ſecretly accept perſons.</hi> Carry it never
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:17110:12"/>ſo ſmoothly, yet if vnder-hand, you preferre a Laick to a Churchman, a Lord to a Plough-man, a kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to a ſtranger, a Courtier to a peaſant, and take away the righteouſneſſe of the innocent, God will certainely reproue you, chide, ſmite, curſe you for it, and ſo ſet it on, as no man ſhall be able to take it off; that God that will not ſuffer you to be partiall for the poore, <note place="margin">Iob 13.</note> for himſelfe, will never brooke other warpings, and partialities: Oh, then looke vpward, pervſe your Oth, deale equally betweene party and party, plea and plea; and if you will needs heare any in private, heare the poore man ſpeake, whoſe counſell dares not ſpeake (ſometimes) in publique; and if you will haſten any hence, haſten him who languiſheth, whilſt head and body ſtand a hundred myles a-ſunder. And when you ride circuit, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you remember, that you ride circuit, not poſt, take time to heare poore mens grievances your ſelues, leſt in a Reference, you leaue the Hare in the Hunts-mans-hands, and the Commiſſioner deputed, vmpire the matter, as once they did at <hi>Rome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The <hi>Aedeates &amp; Aricini, &amp;c.</hi>
               </note> betweene Neighbours; the ground is neyther the Plaintifs nor Defendants, it is the Iudges. To wind vp all, nor you, nor wee of the Miniſtry (to whom I had more to ſay if the place ſuited) nor any preſent, haue done the good wee ſhould; let vs ſay for the time paſt, <hi>That we haue beene vnprofitable ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants;</hi> and henceforward, reſolue with the Church, of old; <note place="margin">Nos non cloqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur magnaſed vivimus.</note> 
               <hi>Not to talke, but to liue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The maine diſpatcht, we would ſpeake the reſt, if we could, with one breath. Is God good? Then loue him; <note place="margin">v. <hi>Minut.</hi> in Octav.</note> for, Goodneſſe is the obiect of loue:
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:17110:12"/>now loue is a deſire of vnion, it vnites vs to God, by conforming and transforming vs, ſo that then our loue ſhall appeare to be true, when out of a deſire to be made one with God, wee conforme to his ordinances, and be transformed into his image.</p>
            <p>Againe, is God good? then let him be iuſtified, and every mouth ſtopped; we inſtance.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">As <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>llar:</hi> and <hi>Wright,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers charge vs.</note> Firſt, ſinnes are committed; Doe me make God a cauſe of it? What as much as man? What more then man? What more then Sathan? O blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie! O impudencie! Did it ever come into any of our hearts ſo to thinke? No, no, we yeeld that ſinne cannot comport with a glorified eſtate, much leſſe with glory it ſelfe: Wee hold, that God being goodneſſe it ſelfe, and All-ſufficiency, cannot be a cauſe, either morall or Phyſicall, of that which is (formally) nothing but deficiency; and if our owne words may not be taken in our owne cauſe, let ſome conſult SVAREZ, <note place="margin">v. <hi>Suar: Opuſ.</hi> v. <hi>Arm:</hi> Theſ. <hi>Vorſt:</hi> Apol: Pro eccl. Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod.</note> and their owne Schooles; others their <hi>Arminius,</hi> and <hi>Verſtius,</hi> and then tell vs, what wee ſay more then they, or they leſſe then we (for ſubſtance) about the cauſe of ſinne.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the world (Chriſtian) is embroyled, yet God is good; in this Confuſion he ſeeth order, and in this double-faced world, the ſide to God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward is <hi>beautifull,</hi> when that to-vs-ward is <hi>defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, Diſputes ariſe, touching Reprobation, which trench farre vpon Gods rights; ſay ſtill, he is good, all that he decrees and does is of himſelfe,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:17110:13"/>and for himſelfe, and therefore beſt, becauſe from, and for the beſt.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Diſcontents ariſe; ſay ſtill, God is good; the times are hard, yet he is good; men are nought, yet he is good; we haue our wants; yet he is good to vs, and where can we mend our ſelues? Were we in <hi>France,</hi> in <hi>Bohemia,</hi> in <hi>Polonia;</hi> nay, were we not Chriſtians but Heathens, not men but beaſts, not beaſts, but ghoſts in hell, twere dutie to ſay, God is good (for where power, juſtice, wiſedome are, there goodneſſe is) and if goodneſſe muſt be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged there, muſt it not in <hi>England,</hi> the face of <hi>Europe;</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> the eye of <hi>England?</hi> Behold, the Creatures refreſht with GODS goodneſſe tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph; the Fields laugh; the Corne ſings; the Birds chirp; <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Plut.</hi> of <hi>tranq.</hi> of mind.</note> the Beaſts skip; yea, (ſayth the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then) we loue to heare them ſing, not howle, not roare, not bellow; and ſhall we (in the midſt of their rejoycing) whine and cry? Doubtleſſe, what ever the times be, or our eſtates be, God is good; and goodneſſe is excellent, and excellency chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lengeth honour, therefore doe the LORD right. <hi>How ever it be</hi> (ſayth the Prophet) <hi>God is good to Iſraell;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 73.1.</note> Let the <hi>Iſraell of God</hi> taſte it, reliſh it, confeſſe it, <note place="margin">Pſal. 34.</note> liue in the ſtrength of it, die in the ſence of it, and ever continue in the feare of Goodneſſe, as <hi>Hoſea</hi> ſpeakes, <hi>Cap.</hi> 3. <hi>vlt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thus farre of Goodneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:17110:13"/>
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Gods Mercie.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow followes the ſecond; <hi>Mercie.</hi> Where, firſt, the thing: ſecondly, the adjunct. For the firſt, though (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) be ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what Generall, yet our Tranſlation is juſtified by our Saviour, <hi>Math.</hi> 9.13. who renders it (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) ſecondly, by our Prophet, who ſevers it from goodneſſe; this being a generall <hi>Mercie,</hi> that a particular <hi>Goodneſſe,</hi> reſpecting miſery and want.</p>
               <p>For the ſecond, tis <hi>Everlaſting;</hi> everlaſtingneſſe (or eternitie) is a perfect poſſeſſion all at once of an endleſſe life (ſayth <hi>Boeth:</hi>) Everlaſting <hi>Mercy</hi> then is perfect <hi>Mercy,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">De Conſola.</note> which ſhuts out all the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections of time, beginning, end, ſucceſſion, and ſuch is Gods mercy. Firſt, his <hi>Eſſentiall mercy</hi> is ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtingnes it ſelfe; for it is himſelfe, and God hath not, but is, things; he is beginning, end, being, and that which is of himſelfe, and ever himſelfe, is eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie it ſelfe: ſecondly, his <hi>Relatiue mercy</hi> (which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects vs, and makes impreſſion on vs) is everlaſting too, in a ſenſe; for the Creatures, ever ſince they had being in him or exiſtence in their naturall cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, did ever and ever well need Mercy, either pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving or conſerving. Mercy in the firſt ſenſe, is <hi>Negatiuely endleſſe,</hi> that is, vncapable of end, becauſe vnboundable for being: in the ſecond ſenſe, it is
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:17110:14"/>
                  <hi>Privatiuely endleſſe,</hi> it ſhall never actually take end, though in it ſelfe it may, and ſome wayes is boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; the firſt is included in the latter, but the latter chiefely here entended; and therefore the Point ariſes to be this<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>2</label> 
                  <hi>Gods mercy (chiefly to his Church) is an endleſſe Mercie,</hi> it knowes no end, receiues no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terruption. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>
                  </label> Reaſons hereof from the Word are theſe, (for as touching teſtimony this Pſalme ſhall be our ſecuritie) <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> firſt, from <hi>Gods nature; he is good. Mercy pleaſes him.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mic. 7.18.</note> Firſt, it is no trouble for him to exerciſe mercy: ſecondly, It is his delight; wee are never weary of receiving, therefore he cannot be of giuing; for, as it is a more bleſſed thing to giue then to receiue; ſo, God takes more content in that, then we in this. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, from <hi>his vnchangea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble word and covenant, thus ſayth the Lord,</hi> though the Mountaines ſhould remoue, &amp;c: and though my Covenant with the Heavens ſhould fayle, yet not this. <hi>Eſay.</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, <hi>From our need;</hi> Every Creature is compounded of <hi>perfection</hi> and <hi>imperfection:</hi> the firſt, is the ground, the ſecond is the Object of Mercie; for the firſt, that which moues to mercie is <hi>proprietie,</hi> therefore we pitie man, becauſe he is our owne fleſh, <note place="margin">Eſa. 58.7.</note> therefore a Chriſtian man, becauſe we be in the bodie. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb. 13.2.</hi> Amat nos tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam aliquid ſui, <hi>Aquinas.</hi>
                  </note> We pittie ſtill our owne, and therefore God ſhewes mercie to vs, becauſe he hath an intereſt in vs, and we be his owne, either as crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, or children, and ſo concur with him in ſome degree of perfection: for the ſecond; the Obiect of Mercy, <note place="margin">v. <hi>Aqui:</hi> ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da ſecundae q. 30. &amp;c.</note> is not miſery, vnleſſe in (the Schoole-mans ſence, that is) a generall ſenſe, but defectiueneſſe; for whatſoever hath not all things in, of, by it ſelfe,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:17110:14"/>ſtands ever at the mercy of another; and in theſe circumſtances ſtands every Creature, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>As compoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded</hi> ex ente &amp; non ente.</note> he partly is and is not, and therefore needes, and therefore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiues mercy from God, where he entends its per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuitie.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſes. </seg>1</label> Now, is Gods mercy thus <hi>Endleſſe?</hi> then (to ſay nothing of thoſe vncouth diſputes, touching that Apocryphall invocation of Saints, <note place="margin">De vener: ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorum.</note> as <hi>Eccius</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeth it touching exciſion and interciſion of grace, the precedency of ſome Creatures aboue Chriſt, in point of Mercy, and other the like mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of opinion and blaſphemie) Let vs learne of the Church, to dwell vpon the mercies of God; here a man may let out himſelfe without danger; God offers more mercie to our eyes then we can ſee; to our thoughts, then we can conceiue; and when we haue done all, he <hi>is aboue all prayſes:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Neh. 9.</note> here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by our hearts will be wonne to God; power with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out mercy, amazes, wiſedome confounds, juſtice affrights, but mercie ſeene in all (as in this <hi>Pſalme</hi>) vnites and melts, here is daily employment, for he lades vs daily with bleſſings, and his mercies are <hi>freſh every morning;</hi> we provoke him, <note place="margin">Lam. 3.</note> and he is <hi>pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent;</hi> we put him to it, and he is <hi>clement;</hi> we be emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and he is <hi>bountifull;</hi> we be miſerable, and he is <hi>pitifull,</hi> good to our bodies, ſoules, eſtates, names, friends, townes, Church, State, Court, Kingdome: Oh, let theſe Mercies ſoke into our hearts, till they draw forth teares, as they did from <hi>Bradford; Let the houſe of Levi ſay, his Mercie endures for ever; Let the houſe of Iudah ſay, his Mercie endures for ever;</hi> Let the <hi>fields</hi> ſay, it is his mercy that we be not all ſpoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led;
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:17110:15"/>led; Let our <hi>Cities</hi> ſay, it is his mercy that we be not all burnt; Let our <hi>Churches</hi> ſay, it is his mercie that we be not all raſde, yea, let this <hi>Land</hi> (of all Lands) ſay, it is his mercie that ſword and fire and peſtilence, and other miſeries, doe not prey vpon mee, as vpon my Siſter-Kingdomes; <hi>O Lord, who is a God like to thee?</hi> thus to beare thus to bleſſe; had not thy Mercies exceeded all limits, our ſinnes ere this had ſunke vs all.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Is God <hi>ever mercifull?</hi> Then the Argument is ever good, <note place="margin">Ioel 2. Iona 3. &amp;c. Rom. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Turne to the Lord</hi> ſay the Prophets, <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent</hi> ſaies the Apoſtle, this the vſe, that Mercy muſt be put to, the better God hath bin to vs, the more wee muſt bleede vnder his reproofes; <hi>O my people</hi> ſaies God <hi>Mich. 6.3.—6. &amp;c.</hi> hee ſpake it once to Iudah, now to England, <hi>O my people,</hi> what is the matter that I cannot winne you? Wherein haue I wronged your Names that you teare mine? When did I grieue you that you grieue mee? when was I hard to you, that you ſo hardly affoord me one day in ſeven? What ayles you, what ayles you, that you will not be ruled by me? I would haue you leaue your ſinnes, you will not; I would haue you holy, happy, you will not, I would haue a Covenant of Salt betwixt vs, that I might never leaue you, you will not; no words, no ſtroakes, no fights abroad, no loue, no kindneſſe, no patience at home can melt you.</p>
               <p>O that yet, yet, yet we of this land would meete the Lord and make our peace with him, whileſt peace is in our gates. Now what the whole Land in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, that this Chamber in perticular muſt doe,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:17110:15"/>I will ſuppoſe your Government, your ſelues pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, to bee good, but what ſhall wee ſay of many in the Citty? I muſt turne to <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22. and ſpeake that to our <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> which the Prophet there doth to his <hi>London. In thee are they that make Idols,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">v. 3.4 7 &amp;c.</note>
                  <hi>in thee they ſhed blood, in thee they ſet light by Father and Mother, in thee they oppreſſe, in thee they deſpiſe my Holineſſe, and prophane my Sabbothes, in thee they carry tales, they cate vppon the Mountaines, in thee they commit Whoredome and abhominable filthineſſe, in thee they take bribes and vſury, in thee thy Rulers take diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honeſt gaine, thy Prieſts hide their Eyes from my Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bothes, thy Prophets daube with vntempered Morter, thy people</hi> (generally) <hi>vexe, oppreſſe, rob, and wrong one another;</hi> thus the Prophet then: now I report my ſelfe to you, whether a Prophet may not ſtill take vp his words againſt this place, &amp; if ſo, then heare what the Lord further adds <hi>I ſought for a man among them that ſhould ſtand in the gap for the Land.</hi> O vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakeable Patience and Mercie, when they ſought not God, God ſought them, when the moſt were deſperate, hee ſought for ſome fewe to ſtand in the breach, and a few ſhould haue ranſomed multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes. Now then (Much honoured and beloved) are there any men amidſt you? any that can weepe for the Abhominations of the place? that can pray, and wreſtle with heaven? Let theſe ſtand in the gap, Let theſe ſtand betweene the living and the dead with their Cenſers, Let them lie betwizt the Porch and the Altar, and ſay, <hi>O thou God of Mercies ſpare our Cittie, our houſes, our Churches, our ſtreetes, and bee Mercifull to our ſinnes, for they are great.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:17110:16"/>
               <p>And what I ſay to all, I ſpeake to every one now preſent, <hi>turne:</hi> Ho thou that haſt beene <hi>an Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, a Swearer, an Adulterer, a Wanton, a Murtherer &amp;c:</hi> Make this vſe of Gods patience and kindenes to thee, to wit, <hi>Repent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O but my ſinnes are many? yea, but his mercies are more; O but they are great? his mercies are greater; O but I am exceeding bad; how bad? as <hi>Manaſſes?</hi> he had mercie for him; as <hi>Magdalen?</hi> he had mercie for her; as <hi>Adam?</hi> he had mercie for him; ô but it is now too late, al his mercie is ſpent; no, <hi>his mercie endureth for ever.</hi> Beloved, the Lord hath ſent this day the cheife of Sinners to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime thus much in your eares, that never yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny periſhed for want of mercie in God; be it that thy ſinnes be ſinnes of <hi>darkneſſe,</hi> ſinnes of <hi>death,</hi> of <hi>blood,</hi> of <hi>hell,</hi> yet if thou canſt finde a heart to repent, God will finde in his heart to pardon, ſee thou thy ſinnes, confeſſe, bewaile, abhorre, forſake them, ſeeke thou the face of God, lie at his foote, Call, Crie, <hi>Lord be mercifull to me a ſinner:</hi> get his Sonne, his Image, and new Obedience, and thy caſe is bleſſed, nay if thou canſt not thus repent, yet thirſt, <note place="margin">Math. 5.</note> nay if thou canſt not thirſt, yet mourne, nay if thou canſt not mourne, yet <hi>bee poore in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> and being ſo in truth, the bleſſing is thine, and <hi>the blood of Ieſus Chriſt ſhall cleanſe thee from all,</hi> all, (I ſay againe) all <hi>thy ſinnes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Is God <hi>ever merciful?</hi> then <hi>be ye merciful, as is your heavenly Father,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 5.</note> nay hee doth not onely practiſe mercie but alſo commaunds it, nay commends it, nay rewards it, nay, plagues the neglect of it, even
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:17110:16"/>to vtter deſtruction; your Elder brother <hi>Chriſt</hi> is alſo mercifull, and interprets every kindneſse done to his done to himſelfe, beſides, Mercy graces <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> glads the <hi>Church,</hi> fils her mouth with Gods prayſes, ſtops the mouth of all adverſaries, yea mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy preſerues the afflicted, and refreſheth the bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els; for Strangers, it winns vpon them in point of Religion, for thy ſelfe, it comforts thy Soule as an evidence of thy truth, eaſeth thy body, being a lighter burden then what elſe wil oppreſſe, (fierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and cruelty) crownes thy name, being that grace that exempts from perſecution, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cypt.</hi> de op: &amp; elecmoſ.</note> and is moſt attractiue, improues thine eſtate, ſanctifieth thy preſent portion to thy ſelfe, and ſettles the remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der vpon thy poſteritie; armes thee againſt ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and death <hi>Pſal.</hi> 41. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> againſt oblivion in the graue, <hi>Acts 9. v. 39.</hi> againſt iudgement at the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, <hi>Iames 2. v. 13. Mat. 25.</hi> ſo that if we eyther reſpect our Father, God, or our Saviour, Chriſt, or our Mother the Church, or our brethren, Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, or our obſervers, Enemies, or our owne ſelues and ſoules, here or hereafter, wee muſt be merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</p>
               <p>If you aske me, how this mercie muſt be exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed? I muſt (in this haſt) referre Schollers to the Caſuiſts, and the reſt of you to other Authors, for a fuller anſwere, the ſumme is this: Mercie muſt haue, firſt <hi>a good roote, Faith in God, Loue to God and man:</hi> Secondly, <hi>a good ende, Gods glory, in mans good and our thankes,</hi> not merit, not ſatisfaction, not impetration, as they. Thirdly, a <hi>good rule,</hi> the word muſt order vs, both for <hi>perſons</hi> and <hi>things,</hi> for
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:17110:17"/>
                  <hi>perſons,</hi> wee muſt begin with God, and with the <hi>Macedonians giue our ſelues to him.</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. <hi>v.</hi> 5. that done, wee muſt proceede to the Common State, then to thoſe next, that touch vs neareſt in the ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſts ties; and ſo paſſe on till (like good ſtomacks) wee haue dealt ſomething to the moſt removed members. <hi>For things,</hi> reſpect muſt bee had to the Soule firſt, then to the Name, then to the bodie, then to the eſtate: Fourthly <hi>our Almes muſt be good</hi> for the matter of it, firſt, in it ſelfe being <hi>wholeſome</hi> and <hi>our owne,</hi> next for the receiver, being ſuted to his needs, (for the purpoſe) comfort, if tempted, Counſell, if diſtracted, ſuccour, if oppreſſed, clothes if naked, eyther worke or a whippe, if Idle.</p>
               <p>Would you knowe (in the third place) what mercy you muſt ſhew? I anſwere ſuch a mercie as God ſhewes, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> firſt <hi>vniverſall mercie,</hi> to mens ſoules; bodies, eſtates, and (that which the worlds is little acquainted with) ſpecially towards Rulers, mercie to mens Names.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, <hi>Everlaſting mercie,</hi> the righteous (ſaith <hi>David</hi>) is <hi>ever giving, lending &amp;c.</hi> Alaſſe Mercie breakes now as faſt as trading, faire houſes be ſhut in, mercy is runne the Countrie, and is like to periſh, for it will hardly line without a houſe; where a poore houſe is kept, there is ſomething for mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie to feede and worke vpon, ſome raggs, ſome ſcraps, ſome fewell, ſome thing; but when (Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das-like) all wee touch is gold, our bread gold, our fewell gold, all turned into the penny, I meane ſo, that we cannot giue, till wee haue paſt through three or foure Lockes, and ſcene and felt our almes,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:17110:17"/>then certainely wee ſhall part with it moſt vnwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly. The houſe-keeper (if he want not an heart (hath opportunities more then any, for the exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of mercy; be not yee wearie of this well do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the World (I know) is importunate in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſons, and impudent in preſſures vpon the free hearted, but doe you your duties, and feare not Swine that are well neyther full nor faſting.</p>
               <p>Now as Houſe-keepers, ſo others in their places muſt be ever mercifull; all ever receiue mercy, Let all ever ſhew; all haue opportunities, let all appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend them; <hi>the poore</hi> (ſayth our bleſſed Saviour) <hi>are ever with you,</hi> if ever, now. Mercy needes not ride abroad to ſeeke worke in theſe dayes ſtep but into thy Neighbours houſe, and thou ſhalt finde po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertie in the Chimney, in the Cupboard, leaneſſe ſitting on the Cheekes, and cleaving to the ribbs of old and yong. O but wee haue not for them? Why wheres the want? your houſes be as trim, as ever, your Children as fine, your Tables as full, your waſtfulneſſe as much as ever, and can you be ever near, nay ever prodigall, and not ever mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull? Whats become of Religion now? Is all tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into words, as once in Saint <hi>Iames</hi> his time? Time was when Chriſtians would ſell their plate Chalices, their Roabes and Iewels, their Lands and poſſeſſions to relieve the Churches neceſſity, and ſhall not we parte with ſuperfluities? tell mee (you that reade Saint <hi>Iohn</hi>) how you ſatisfie his queſtion, and your owne Conſciences? <note place="margin">1. Iohn 3.17.</note> if any Man hath theſe worlds goods, and ſees his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:17110:18"/>ther want &amp;c. how dwels the loue of God in him? Will you ſay, wee haue not this Worldes goods? Then diſſemble not, now yee ſtand in a croſſe poynt to good <hi>Araunah,</hi> hee ſpent like a Subject, gaue like a King; <note place="margin">2. Sam. 24.23</note> you build fayre, goe like Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and will you giue like Bankrupts? Nay your Tavernes, your Feaſtes, and Playes, will riſe vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you: you haue meanes to feaſt the Rich, and doe not you remember Chriſts Cavear, <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie before kindneſſe?</hi> You haue a pinte of wine for any Friend, and not a penny for Chriſt? you can finde a Teſter for ſome game, ſome ſhewe, ſome ſtage Play, and what, nothing for Mercy? Or will yon ſay wee ſee no neede? Why, what elſe can you ſee? Men want ſtocke, want bread, want worke, want money, and when that is deare, nothing is cheape, and is not heere neede? but there is no extremitie? Woe is mee, there be many at her ſtay, I haue a little meale and oyle in a Cruyce, <note place="margin">1. Reg. 17.12.</note> I will bake, eate, die, they are now ſinking, ſinking, if you come not quickly to their ſuccour, they are loft, is not this an extremitie? But where bee meanes? finde you hearts, I will yet finde meanes.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, <hi>the Backe</hi> may lend you ſomething, your golden fingers might cloath ſome, and bee never the Colder, your great Ruffes might feede others, and be never the vnhandſomer, the Groues and Grownds vpon your backes (as <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſpeakes) might lodge others, <note place="margin">De habit: mul: &amp; li. de cult. Faem.</note> and yet ſitt never the worſe vpon your owne and childrens backs.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, <hi>the Belly</hi> might ſpare you ſomething
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:17110:18"/>with advantage to your health, and ſtrength, one meale ſaved in a weeke, one diſh at a meale, one cup of wine, one pipe of Tobacco in a day would come to ſomething in the yeare. I quake to thinke what Chriſtians wee be, ſome ſurfet, ſome ſtarue, all at once; rather then we will not pine the poore, wee will cramme and choake our ſelues.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, <hi>our Houſes</hi> might lend vs ſomething, for howſoever (with them of old) wee feede, as if wee would die preſently, yet wee build as if we would liue for ever: It is a world to ſee how cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious wee be in ſuting every Roome, whileſt the members of Chriſt goe not like one Fathers chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, nay it is not neceſſary they ſhould bee all in a Sute, onely if Chriſt may be heard, hee that hath two coates, ſhould giue one to the naked.</p>
               <p> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, <hi>borrow of our Enemie Sinne,</hi> and here if you will not hold, I know not what to ſay, but that, the Heathen ſayth, <note place="margin">Senec.</note> 
                  <hi>hee is a bad Phiſitian that deſpayres of his cure;</hi> wee haue money for braules, for bribes, for the feeding of pride, revenge, am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, luſt, and ſhall we feede foes, &amp; ſtarue friends? let me ſpeake it once for all, had we as much zeale to mercy, as to ſinne, to men, as to birds and mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kies, to Chriſtians and Preachers, as to Claw-backs, Ieſters, Fidlers, Fooles, we would finde meanes to relieue them; meanes for the preſent, but how ſhall our owne doe hereafter? Why, is not mercy as ſure a graine as vanitie? Is God like to breake? ſayth not he, <hi>Hee that giues to the poore, lends to the Lord, and he will pay him?</hi> I haue nothing to ſpare;
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:17110:19"/>thou haſt for thy friends, for Gods Enemies, Pride, Vanity, if none for Chriſt; receiue thy doome, <hi>Hee that ſtops has eare at the crie of the Poore &amp;c.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro 21.13. Iames 2.13.</note> 
                  <hi>Iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment without mercie, to him that ſhewed no mercy, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from mee yee curſed,</hi> you had meate, drinke, cloath, houſe-roome, for ſinfull men, horſes, doggs, carts, none for mee. But the poore bee as ſine as my ſelfe? I pray thee, be ſayd with reaſon; if others be not ſit to receiue, thou art not tyed to giue; If thou bee fit to giue, and they to receiue, diſpute no longer, rather heare the Apoſtle, <hi>Put on the bowels of mercy,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Col. 3.12. verſe 5.</note> and to that ende take his directions, firſt ſlay vnmortified luſts, next ſteepe thy thoughts <hi>in the Mercies of God,</hi> and they will dye thine, <note place="margin">Ephe. 318.19.</note> as the dye-fart doth the cloath, that done, be rich in faith and good workes; firſt, in the <hi>Inwarce actes</hi> of mercy, pittie the afflicted, bleede with them, mourne with them, thirſt their good, caſt their good. Secondly, <hi>In outward acts</hi> of mercy, goe to them, ſitt with them, pray for them, lend them, ſpeake for them, giue them, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue them, and if all thy abilitie amount but to one cupp of cold water it ſhall bee accepted rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. <note place="margin">Math. 10.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Laſtly, God is <hi>ever mercifull,</hi> let vs then leaue the labouring Church in his <hi>everlaſting armes as Moſes ſpeakes.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deut. 33.27.</note> Lets recommend our Iſraell to him, whoſe mercy hath prevented and will preſerve vs, if wee conſtantly flie vnto him, and let every one that is capable of mercy, <hi>being Fatherleſſe,</hi> that hath obtained mercy, <note place="margin">Hoſ. 14.3</note>
                  <hi>being Penitent, and Mercifull,</hi>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:17110:19"/>ſtay himſelfe here: <hi>The Mercy of God endureth for ever,</hi> my ſtrength may faile, my eſtate may, my friends may, my outward comforts, my inward feelings may, but the Mercies of God never fayle, all miſeries haue an ende, Gods Mercie (which is my Mercie) is endleſſe, is boundleſſe: It endures for ever. (⸫)</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
